If you want to change the world, start by making your bed.
अगर आप दुनिया को बदलना चाहते हैं, तो सबसे पहले अपना बिस्तर ठीक करें।
If you make your bed every morning, you will have accomplished the first task of the day.
अगर आप हर सुबह अपना बिस्तर ठीक करते हैं, तो आप दिन का पहला काम पूरा कर लेंगे।
It will give you a small sense of pride,
इससे आपको थोड़ा गर्व महसूस होगा,
and it will encourage you to do another task,
और यह आपको एक और काम करने के लिए प्रोत्साहित करेगा,
and by the end of the day, that one task completed,
और दिन के अंत तक वह एक काम पूरा हो जाने के बाद,
will have turned into many tasks completed.
छोटे-छोटे काम पूरे हो जाएँगे।
Making your bed will also reinforce the fact
अपना बिस्तर ठीक करना इस तथ्य को भी पुष्ट करेगा
that little things in life matter. If you can't do the little things right,
कि जीवन में छोटी-छोटी चीजें मायने रखती हैं, अगर आप छोटी-छोटी चीजें सही से नहीं कर सकते, तो
you will never do the big things right. And if by chance you have a miserable day,
आप कभी भी बड़ी चीजें सही से नहीं कर पाएँगे, और अगर संयोग से आपका दिन खराब रहा, तो
you will come home to a bed that is made,
आप घर आकर अपने द्वारा बनाया हुआ बिस्तर पाएँगे,
and a made bed gives you encouragement that tomorrow will be better.
और एक बना हुआ बिस्तर आपको यह प्रोत्साहन देता है कि कल बेहतर होगा।
I've been a Navy SEAL for 36 years. Every morning in basic SEAL training,
मैं 36 साल से नौसेना सील हूँ, सील प्रशिक्षण के दौरान हर सुबह,
my instructors, who at the time were all Vietnam veterans, would come into my barracks room
मेरे प्रशिक्षक, जो उस समय सभी वियतनाम के दिग्गज थे, मेरे बर्न रूम में आते थे
and the first thing they would inspect was your bed.
और सबसे पहले वे मेरे बिस्तर का निरीक्षण करते थे।
If you did it right, the corners would be square, the covers pulled tight,
अगर आप इसे सही तरीके से करते, तो कोने चौकोर होते, कवर कसकर खींचे जाते,
the pillow centered just under the headboard
तकिए का केंद्र हेडबोर्ड के ठीक नीचे होता
and the extra blanket folded neatly at the foot of the rack.
और अतिरिक्त कंबल रैक के पैर पर बड़े करीने से मोड़ा जाता।
It was a simple task,
यह एक सरल कार्य था,
mundane at best, but every morning we were required to make our bed to perfection.
सबसे अच्छा सांसारिक, लेकिन हर सुबह हमें अपना बिस्तर पूरी तरह से ठीक करना होता था।
It seemed a little ridiculous at the time,
उस समय यह थोड़ा हास्यास्पद लगता था,
particularly in light of the fact that we were aspiring to be real warriors,
खासकर इस तथ्य के प्रकाश में कि हम असली योद्धा,
tough battle-hardened SEALs.
कठोर युद्ध के लिए तैयार सील बनने की आकांक्षा रखते थे।
But the wisdom of this simple act has been proven to me many times over.
लेकिन इस सरल कार्य की बुद्धिमत्ता मेरे लिए कई बार साबित हुई है
.
।
It doesn't matter if you've ever served in uniform or not.
इससे कोई फर्क नहीं पड़ता कि आपने कभी वर्दी में सेवा की है या नहीं।
It doesn't matter what your gender, ethnic or religious background,
इससे कोई फर्क नहीं पड़ता कि आपका लिंग, आपकी जातीय या धार्मिक पृष्ठभूमि,
your orientation or your social status.
आपका रुझान या आपकी सामाजिक स्थिति क्या है।
Our struggles in this world are similar,
इस दुनिया में हमारे संघर्ष समान हैं,
and the lessons to overcome those struggles and move forward,
और उन संघर्षों को दूर करने और आगे बढ़ने,
to change ourselves and the world around us will apply equally to all.
खुद को बदलने और अपने आस-पास की दुनिया को बदलने के सबक सभी पर समान रूप से लागू होंगे।
If you think it's hard to change the lives of ten people,
अगर आपको लगता है कि 10 लोगों के जीवन को बदलना,
to change their lives forever, you're wrong.
उनके जीवन को हमेशा के लिए बदलना मुश्किल है, तो आप गलत हैं।
I saw it happen every day in Iraq and Afghanistan,
मैंने इसे इराक और अफगानिस्तान में हर दिन होते देखा है,
but changing the world can happen anywhere and anyone can do it.
लेकिन दुनिया को बदलना कहीं भी हो सकता है और कोई भी कर सकता है।
So what starts here can indeed change the world?
तो यहां से जो शुरू होता है वह वास्तव में दुनिया को बदल सकता है?
You will likely fail often. It will be painful, it will be discouraging.
आप अक्सर असफल हो सकते हैं। यह दर्दनाक होगा, यह हतोत्साहित करने वाला होगा।
At times you will be tested many times.
कई बार यह आपकी परीक्षा लेगा।
In the darkest moment of the mission, you need to be calm,
मिशन के उस सबसे अंधेरे क्षण में आपको शांत रहने की आवश्यकता होती है,
when you must be calm, when you must be composed, when you must use all your tactical skills,
जब आपको शांत रहना चाहिए, जब आपको संयमित होना चाहिए, जब आपको अपने सभी सामरिक कौशल,
your physical strength and your inner strength.
अपनी शारीरिक शक्ति और अपनी आंतरिक शक्ति को काम में लाना चाहिए।
If you want to change the world,
यदि आप दुनिया को बदलना चाहते हैं, तो
you must be your very best in the darkest moments.
आपको सबसे अंधेरे क्षणों में अपना सर्वश्रेष्ठ प्रदर्शन करना चाहिए।
If I've learned anything in my travels around the world,
अगर मैंने दुनिया की यात्रा करते हुए कुछ सीखा है,
it's the power of hope, the power of one person,
तो वह है उम्मीद की शक्ति, एक व्यक्ति की शक्ति,
a Washington, a Lincoln, King, Mandela and even a young girl from Pakistan,
एक वाशिंगटन, एक लिंकन, किंग, मंडेला और यहां तक कि पाकिस्तान की एक छोटी लड़की,
Malala, one person can change the world by giving people hope.
मलाला, एक व्यक्ति लोगों को उम्मीद देकर दुनिया को बदल सकता है।
Start each day with a task completed,
प्रत्येक दिन को कार्य पूरा करने के साथ शुरू करें,
find someone to help you through life, respect everyone,
जीवन में आपकी मदद करने के लिए किसी को खोजें, सभी का सम्मान करें,
know that life is not fair and that you will fail often,
जानें कि जीवन उचित नहीं है और आप अक्सर असफल होंगे,
but if you take some risks, step up when times are toughest, face down...
लेकिन यदि आप कुछ जोखिम लेते हैं, तो सबसे कठिन समय में आगे बढ़ें, सामना करें...
lift up the downtrodden and never, ever give up.
निराश लोगों को उठाएं और कभी हार न मानें।
If you do these things,
यदि आप ये काम करते हैं, तो
then the next generation and the generations that follow
अगली पीढ़ी और उसके बाद आने वाली पीढ़ियां
will live in a world far better than the one we have today
आज की तुलना में कहीं बेहतर दुनिया में रहेंगी
and what started here will indeed have changed the world for the better.
और यहां जो शुरू हुआ है, उसने वास्तव में दुनिया को बेहतर के लिए बदल दिया है।
At the end of SEAL training, there is a bell,
अंत में सील प्रशिक्षण में, एक घंटी होती है,
a brass bell that hangs in the center of the compound for all the students to see,
एक पीतल की घंटी जो सभी छात्रों को दिखाने के लिए परिसर के केंद्र में लटकी होती है,
all you have to do to quit is ring the bell.
आपको बस इतना करना है कि घंटी बजाएं।
Ring the bell and you no longer have to wake up at 5 o'clock,
घंटी बजाएं और आपको फिर पांच बजे जागने की जरूरत नहीं है,
ring the bell and you no longer have to do the freezing cold swims,
घंटी बजाएं और आपको फिर ठंड में तैरने की जरूरत नहीं है,
ring the bell and you no longer have to do the runs, the obstacle course, the PT
घंटी बजाएं और आपको फिर दौड़, बाधा कोर्स, पीटी
and you no longer have to endure the hardships of training,
नहीं करनी है और आपको फिर प्रशिक्षण की कठिनाइयों को नहीं सहना है,
all you have to do to quit is ring the bell,
आपको बस बाहर निकलने के लिए घंटी बजानी है,
if you want to change the world,
यदि आप दुनिया को बदलना चाहते हैं, तो
don't ring
न बजाएं
the bell
घंटी